<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <link>http://sathishmanohar.com</link>
    <atom:link href="http://sathishmanohar.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description></description>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2015 18:40:50 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2015 18:40:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>

    
    
    <item>
      <title>You don't need countries and governments</title>
      <link>http://sathishmanohar.com/articles/you-dont-need-countries-and-governments/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://sathishmanohar.com/articles/you-dont-need-countries-and-governments</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I live in Chennai, India. The city experienced unprecedented rainfall and flood, because of which hundreds of people died and hundreds of thousands of people have lost their home and property. Even after a week, some parts of the city haven’t recovered completely. People who lived a healthy and peaceful life in their homes are living in camps without adequate food, water and sanitation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this one week period, I learned and noticed a lot of things. Many incidents validated the assumptions I have held for a long time about society and governance. That is, you don’t need to demarcate land into countries or states for a healthy and functioning society. The political unit called country has become a bottleneck in advancement of human civilization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may think I’m crazy. But it really isn’t that crazy an idea. Let’s analyze from different angles as to why countries aren’t needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-a-country&quot;&gt;What is a country?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now may remember that one question during exams which we would always answer correctly and get that easiest one mark - “What is your country?” But have you ever come across the question: “What is a country?” No? Why is that? Because the answer is ugly and something you are not supposed to think too much about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what is a country? A country is a coercive monopoly over a certain geographic area. Sure, there are structures like democracy, in which it seems like people are voting for candidates of their choice, and thus they are in control of their country. But nothing could be farther from the truth. Having people choose its administrators doesn’t change the fact that a government is a coercive monopoly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;governments-are-evil-so-is-democracy&quot;&gt;Governments are evil, so is democracy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On paper it all seems fine. There are people, and they choose some people from among them to manage the country, and everybody is happy. But when you think even a little, you can find the obvious flaws in this system. First of all, there are no ‘people’; there are only a collection of individuals with conflicting interests. The use of the word people cleverly hides the reality and clubs us as a group of individuals with uniform mindset and common interests. That, of course, is not true. There are no people, only individuals and groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, you have to look at how ‘the people’ choose the administrators in a democracy. A certain percentage of people vote for contesting candidates from different parties, and whoever gets a majority gets to run the country. So, what is wrong with this system? It is a handful of people chosen by the majority voters making rules for all the people including the people who voted against them and for those who didn’t vote at all. It is oppression 101. Yet most of the democracies don’t feel oppressive. Why? There are two main reasons for it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The arguments and debates between political parties are often on topics not directly related to the common man’s needs, and any outcome will not have a direct impact on their lives. Examples: abortion, death penalty, eating beef. If you are wondering about solutions for these, we’ll see that under law.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Humanity in general has grown more civil and tolerant regardless of what your favorite news channel wants you to think. Please take the time to look at the data, and not the sensationalized content that manipulates you into feeling constant fear.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also why, although the very structure of government is oppressive, you don’t feel the oppression; because there isn’t much to feel oppressed about anymore. We humans have grown more civilized and tolerant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;country-is-an-abstract-concept&quot;&gt;Country is an abstract concept&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides, just because the land you live on exists, it doesn’t mean the country is also a material reality. A country is an abstract idea that exists in the mind just like religion is an idea that exists only in the mind. But religions are not coercive anymore. Religions, for the most part, have grown tolerant and embrace other religions, but that is not the case with countries. If countries become tolerant and embrace competition by allowing other countries to operate within a given geography, then the boundaries between different countries will blur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-law-cannot-work&quot;&gt;The law cannot work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For thousands of years, humans have been making laws to manage societies and civilizations but none of them are implemented completely; yet we still keep making these laws.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laws cannot be pre-determined to guide our actions under all circumstances. At the most, we can only have abstract, overarching guidelines, and each case must be decided on its own merit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;controlling-dishonesty-and-theft-in-a-lawless-land&quot;&gt;Controlling dishonesty and theft in a lawless land&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theft is a simple problem. There is an economic incentive in theft; take the incentive away, and theft becomes unattractive. When your possession is stolen, there is no just correlation between the value of property and the punishment in the present system. I’ve seen records of women who serve months in prison for stealing baby food. All thefts are not the same. Every case should be treated in relation to the actual crime and the punishment should fit the crime. Make the thief compensate the robbed with the value of the stolen good plus the cost of pursuing the thief. Theft becomes no longer an economically viable option, compared to the present day system in which the thief is not required to pay back the damages and the punishment given is shelter and food at somebody else’s expense. On top of that, providing easy entry into the job market for criminals and helping them gain a good social standing is also a great way to reduce theft. There can be commercial establishments who can undertake such risky proposition, provided they are properly incentivized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General perception of honest and dishonest behavior varies hugely between different groups and should be left to their discretion as long as they don’t violate the overarching values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-court-system&quot;&gt;The court system&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a society not controlled by the government, we need individual private entities, big and small, to provide essential services currently offered by government. Of this, the court system is a significant one. The court system is really an arbitration system that claims to provide just arbitration for every problem under the sun. But privatized arbitration companies can evolve and specialize in particular domains and provide just arbitration in their area of specialization. For example, family dispute centers, technological dispute centers, financial dispute centers, property dispute centers, inheritance dispute centers are some of specialty arbitration services possible. It’ll work like any other commercial service, for which you pay a service fee like any other commercial service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-police&quot;&gt;The police&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main functions of the police in most countries are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;policing the neighborhood&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;providing security for groups or individuals when necessary&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;collecting evidence after a crime and submitting them during arbitration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of these three, policing neighborhood and security services are already available from private establishments; collecting and submitting evidence for arbitration has to be properly privatized. Doing this vastly reduces the unchecked power police all over the world has. Because it is a private system, the policeman is like any other member of the working force like a carpenter, engineer or doctor who does not have a government to provide immunity for his actions. It’ll help in achieving a decent and reasonable police force.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;taxes&quot;&gt;Taxes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to pay taxes in a government-free society. Duh. Taxes are how government extorts money from its citizens. After extracting your money you have no say in how the government spends your money. In a governmentless society, everyone is entitled to what they earn and they can spend it only on goods, services or charity they choose to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;greedy-people-and-corporations&quot;&gt;Greedy people and corporations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the present financial climate, it is natural to think if such a system comes to effect, then greedy people and corporations would become giant services and would similarly extract money from people through unethical business practices. But, the current government controlled society is the one that created those giant corporations by creating regulations that automatically create a big barrier to entry with it. But in a non-government controlled society, business won’t be regulated by law but by price and competition; with competition, people and corporations cannot afford to be too greedy or else they’ll lose their business to their competitors. So, a free market has all the necessary inbuilt mechanisms to provide for a sustainable business environment that is just for both producers and consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;monetary-system&quot;&gt;Monetary system&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Money is a big topic in and by itself. It can also be provided by private methods that is reliable than government issued money. Learn more about bitcoin, It is a decentralized currency that is not controlled by any government but still functions as good as a currency for years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;disaster-relief-and-welfare&quot;&gt;Disaster relief and welfare&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a common misconception that governments are the best equipped to manage relief and welfare during the time of natural or other disasters. But, if you look closely at the incidents around the world, you can clearly see that it is the volunteers and kind human beings who step in to help and go beyond their call of duty. Governments don’t have resources and processes for their existing operations, let alone for a sudden catastrophic event. During the recent Chennai floods, the Government of India committed to Rs. 1000 crore (roughly 150 million USD) while Cognizant, an American multinational corporation and a leading employer in Chennai, has committed Rs. 260 crores (40 million USD). When a company that doesn’t owe anything to the city of Chennai can contribute 1/4th the funds given by the central government, which collects taxes from its citizens on their every salary and their every purchase, it makes you really wonder what purpose countries serve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time-for-anarchy-has-come&quot;&gt;Time for anarchy has come&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Until now, I purposely avoided using the term ‘Anarchy’ because of the stigma attached to it. Anarchy is the word used by media and writers to describe people planning mischief to disrupt a society. But, the word actually means no ruler and it is a viable possibility in which a society can function, and in many ways, a far superior system compared to government-controlled systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of available literature about anarchy that isn’t talked about. If you are one of the many who are fed up with your government, educate yourself and your friends about alternatives as well. Market for Liberty is a great book to get to know more about anarchy, and it’s free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today people think that they are safer because they have a government, in the absence of which everything will go haywire. Pay close attention, and you can see for yourself both the fear and the false sense of security just below the surface isn’t real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is time for us to think outside the boundaries we are taught to think within. Take control of your life and live a fulfilling and happy life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Bitcoin the ultimate fiat currency</title>
      <link>http://sathishmanohar.com/articles/bitcoin-the-ultimate-fiat-currency/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://sathishmanohar.com/articles/bitcoin-the-ultimate-fiat-currency</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever Since humans figured out getting along with one another is the best thing for survival and co-existence, they started trading goods and services. Primitive people lacked sophisticated market and financial systems and they were simply exchanging things of value among each other. This system is known as barter system and it had few problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problem---mutual-value&quot;&gt;Problem - Mutual Value&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parties involving in a transaction should have things of value for each other, otherwise the transaction may not happen.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;E.g.&lt;/strong&gt; If I make wrestling cards and you make jumbo jets, you can’t buy wrestling cards from me if I don’t want your jumbo jet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problem---value-matrix&quot;&gt;Problem - Value Matrix&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parties involving in a transactions should figure out relative value of each others goods or services. This creates huge complexity essentially requiring an infinite matrix of all goods and services in the world to facilitate free trade and to add to the complexity you should account for fluctuation in the market on a constant basis.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;E.g.&lt;/strong&gt; If you are selling your jumbo jet in exchange for wresting cards you should know how many packs of wrestling cards the jet is worth. If you are selling for kittens you should know many kittens its worth. If you are selling for corn flakes, you get the point. right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;problem---value-matching&quot;&gt;Problem - Value Matching&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In certain scenarios value can’t be split easily.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;E.g.&lt;/strong&gt; If we figure your jet is worth 4000 packs of wresting cards and you want to buy 2000 packs from me, how would we split the jet? Thus no transaction would occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;beyond-barter-system&quot;&gt;Beyond barter system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve above problems in barter system merchants figured out it would be easier to have a common commodity that has value to (almost) all parties and trade their goods and services relative to it. Salt and gold were the mostly used two common goods that had value for almost all merchants. Over time salt gradually lost its value due to efficient production but that is another story. So, gold became the  commodity against which all other goods and services were valued against.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gold is harder to carry around and store so there were logistical problems. To work around this people made gold deposits in vaults and traded the receipts instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;money&quot;&gt;Money&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These gold receipts were the first version of modern currency. These receipts were issued by vaults in exchange for gold. These vaults were run by private entities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;governments&quot;&gt;Governments&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As governments gained more power it took over the entire vault system from the hands of private entities and maintained its monopoly over storing of gold and issuance of currency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the earlier days currencies were synonymous with gold receipts. For every unit of money in circulation there was equivalent amount of gold in the vault somewhere which the holder of the money can claim anytime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gold-to-fiat&quot;&gt;Gold to Fiat&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As governments became the sole authority in issuing money, they started printing out more money than there was gold in the vault for various reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As currency started out as receipt for gold, governments had the obligation to give corresponding gold for the currency if a citizen chooses to claim his or her gold. Since governments has printed disproportionate amount of money than the available gold in treasury, they had to do something about the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wD3KYlpE2lk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fiat-currency&quot;&gt;Fiat Currency&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile governments noticed almost no one redeems gold for the currencies and most people of the newer generation doesn’t really know how the whole monetary system really works, they came up with a plan to entirely move away from the gold backed currency system. The gold standard was successfully abolished by president Nixon in 1971. Since then all money issued were not backed by anything but government promise. This type of currency that is not backed by anything of tangible value is called Fiat currency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fiat-works&quot;&gt;Fiat works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though a currency not backed by anything is evil as it gives lot of power to the issuer of currency which in this case is the government. It surprisingly works. It is safe to say almost all the value transactions in the world for the past 50 years were done using fiat currencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fiat currencies demonstrate an interesting phenomenon that we otherwise wouldn’t have discovered. No matter how stupid and evil the underlying mechanics are, the mere act of participating parties believing something has value makes the financial world go round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;bitcoin-the-fiat-currency&quot;&gt;Bitcoin the Fiat currency&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin is an Open Source, decentralized currency that does not require trust in any particular entity. Bitcoin differs from government issued fiat currencies backed by unverifiable government promise by offering more tangible and solid promise backed by math and cryptography that anyone can verify.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;government-fiat-vs-bitcoin&quot;&gt;Government Fiat vs Bitcoin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since government issued currencies are backed by nothing of value, anyone can print a same looking currency bill and start circulating it. In such a scenario there is actually no difference between government issued currency and counterfeit currencies except the issuer, since both of them are backed by nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though Bitcoin is also not backed by anything of tangible value, It delivers on certain promises that government issued fiat does not. Some of them are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;impossible-to-counterfeit&quot;&gt;Impossible to counterfeit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The number of counterfeit Bitcoins in circulation is &lt;em&gt;zero&lt;/em&gt;. Thats right. Since, Bitcoin is based on cryptography and every unit has to be verified for each transaction its impossible to have a counterfeit unit of currency in Bitcoin network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;inflation-control&quot;&gt;Inflation control&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inflation in simple terms is increasing the total amount of money is circulation. Governments inflate the currency by printing more bills. So why is it important to have inflation under control you ask? Lets say there are only 10000 units of currency in circulation and you have 100 of them. That means you have 1% percent of total money supply and you are uber rich, now you probably realize you are not rich because you have 100 units, its because you have relatively large portion of total money in circulation. Lets say government prints another 10000 units, now you still have the same 100 units with you but now you only own 0.5% of the total 20000 units in circulation. Thus increasing the money in circulation makes you poorer even if the amount money you posses doesn’t change. Therefore inflation is a serious problem that needs to be addressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin addresses inflation with a set of rules for adding units to total supply and the total number of units in circulation will never exceed 21 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;low-barrier-to-entry&quot;&gt;Low barrier to entry&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin is an open protocol upon which anyone can easily build tools and services to improve overall experience for Bitcoin users whereas working with government currencies and financial systems requires lot of paperwork and huge overhead because government fiat is not built upon solid foundation and allowing untrusted parties to participate in the ecosystem will render the system broken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fiat-of-the-future&quot;&gt;Fiat of the future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finance world is working with government issued fiat currencies for well over 5 decades midst all its flaws. Now a clearly superior fiat currency has emerged in the form of Bitcoin. It is inevitable, for a superior solution to replace the inferior one. Thus Bitcoin ( or possibly a better alternative cryptocurrency ) will be the standard fiat currency for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to display web pages without HTML or PHP extension</title>
      <link>http://sathishmanohar.com/articles/how-to-display-web-pages-without-html-extension/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://sathishmanohar.com/articles/how-to-display-web-pages-without-html-or-php-extension</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working on plain HTML website, in which I wanted to have URLs without
the &lt;code&gt;.html&lt;/code&gt; extension in the end of the URLs. It turns out its relatively easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In apache &lt;code&gt;.htaccess&lt;/code&gt; file add the below line whereever appropriate&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Options +MultiViews
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Multiview option tries to find a best match for the request received by server
But keep in mind there are priorities in how it handles files types in directories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what I’ve tested the priority is directories first then &lt;code&gt;php&lt;/code&gt; and then
&lt;code&gt;html&lt;/code&gt;. So lets say if you want your server to return &lt;code&gt;example.com/gallery.html&lt;/code&gt;
for the request &lt;code&gt;example.com/gallery&lt;/code&gt; then you should avoid having a &lt;code&gt;gallery&lt;/code&gt;
directory in the same location because the directory will be prioritised and the
server will return the directory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise if you have two files one &lt;code&gt;HTML&lt;/code&gt; and one &lt;code&gt;PHP&lt;/code&gt;. The request without the
file extension will return &lt;code&gt;PHP&lt;/code&gt; since apache by default prioritizes &lt;code&gt;PHP&lt;/code&gt; over
&lt;code&gt;HTML&lt;/code&gt; in Multiviews.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Docker will change everything</title>
      <link>http://sathishmanohar.com/articles/docker-will-change-everything/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://sathishmanohar.com/articles/docker-will-change-everything</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.docker.io/&quot; title=&quot;Docker Official Website&quot;&gt;Docker&lt;/a&gt; is an open-source engine that automates the deployment of any application as a lightweight, portable, self-sufficient container that will run virtually anywhere.
from: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.docker.io/learn_more/&quot; title=&quot;Docker Learn More&quot;&gt;Docker Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yea. But what is docker you ask? Let me try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until now, if you need to run any application in production, you need to have the environment setup with great care with all dependencies in place. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you have a rails application that runs on ubuntu server with ruby 2.0.0, latest version of rails and mysql for database. you need to have production environment setup with all these dependencies and deploy your application on top of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what happens when there is another rails application that uses the same stack. you need to setup &lt;em&gt;another instance&lt;/em&gt; identical to the previous one to run the second application in production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might have sensed the problem docker is trying to solve. Docker tries to make it possible to share underlying resources between applications without stepping on each others toes. To put it even simpler docker tries to make production applications run on shared resources like a desktop user runs several programs inside the same operating system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think docker project is going to have huge impact on several front. I’ll list some of them below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cloud-platforms&quot;&gt;Cloud Platforms&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Current cloud platforms offers on demand scaling and pay for &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; what you use model (but not quite).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;provision-and-build-times&quot;&gt;Provision and Build times&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At present cloud scenario, you need to have a bare minimum instance running all the time to serve any application. Technically as a customer of the cloud provider you are using a less powerful instance even if any of your users are presently not using the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is expected for cloud applications because of attributes related to cloud instances like provision time, build time etc which takes at least few minutes. So you need to have an instance in place just in case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where docker shines a lot, provision time and build time are almost non-existent, even starting a docker container takes less than a second in some cases. This attribute of docker almost eliminates the need for an instance with a dedicated processor, memory and disk space running all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-instance-abstraction&quot;&gt;The instance abstraction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloud providers charge for instances which are virtual isolated operating systems. User pays for these instances for the time they use them. These instances are actually isolated and each of its own, hence charging for instance is justified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a container scenario, the operating system is shared among containers and since there is no need for those containers to have dedicated processor power or memory all the time, the instance abstraction can go away and pay for what you &lt;em&gt;actually use&lt;/em&gt; models can emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specialized service providers like database hosting, image processing providers can hugely benefit from this decoupling from instances. Instead of choosing services in terms of allocated resources, pluggable services charged based on actual service usage can emerge. Finally underlying machine can be abstracted away in favor of actual service metering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pay-by-the-hour-model&quot;&gt;Pay by the hour model&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most cloud hosting companies bill customers by the hour (even if you kill the instance after 15 minutes of use), which is lot better compared to old ways of buying physical dedicated hardware in advance. But, its still not pay for what you use. With a shared resources environment like docker, new hosting companies can emerge that charges only for the CPU cycles and memory actually used by the customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;development-ease&quot;&gt;Development Ease&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up until now, developers are required to maintain different development and production environments. This inconsistency inevitably leads to issues. Docker promises to eliminate this situation by making it possible to develop on the same container that will be deployed in production, which will make development a lot easier and deployment lot less painful.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>We need a web content spec</title>
      <link>http://sathishmanohar.com/articles/we-need-a-web-content-spec/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://sathishmanohar.com/articles/we-need-web-content-spec</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Its been a pain for me choosing a work flow to write web content. Most of the content editors out there are word processors. Problem is word processors were designed a few decades before. The main use case for word processors is to make a digital document which at some point is outputted to a paper, Good old Paper. Word processors are fine for people, who are still involved in computer to paper work flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for someone like me, who almost only writes for web, word processors completely irrelevant. It even seems weird and archaic when I open a word processor for web content. The markup generated my these word processors are mostly garbage. All I care about is content in a schematic markup ready to be pushed to live web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;markdown&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Markdown is the most popular plain text to HTML converter. Markdown is tremendously helpful if you only use the elements markdown supports without utilizing the full power of HTML elements. I love &lt;a href=&quot;http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&quot; title=&quot;MarkDown Project&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt;. In fact I’m writing this in markdown. But, markdown is not without its limitations. For example there is no clear way to represent tabular data in markdown. It is well known that lack of coverage for web content spectrum has created many variants of markdown and implementation issues for many projects and developers and there were attempts to create an unified &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codinghorror.com/blog/2012/10/the-future-of-markdown.html&quot; title=&quot;The Future of Markdown&quot;&gt;markdown spec&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;need-for-content-spec&quot;&gt;Need for Content Spec&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel instead of focusing our efforts on markdown spec, It would be much more beneficial for the wider community if there were a web content spec. It could be a subset of HTML with only elements that are designed for consumption rather than creation or interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;html-for-consumption&quot;&gt;HTML for consumption&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although HTML is one of the most solid specs out there, It has moved quite a bit from the original document (only) model, adding lot of features for the modern web, while I certainly like color pickers and date pickers to be part of HTML. It has moved much farther from the document for consumption approach. This creates a need for a spec that only has the elements mostly used for consumption. The kind of markup that can be pasted anywhere and should just work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-can-a-spec-do&quot;&gt;What can a spec do&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A spec like this will help a great deal for the development of text to HTML syntaxes, Web content editors, and tool sets surrounding content creation for web. Having a spec can finally give a basement for third parties to develop tools for web content creation and will tremendously improve the overall experience for developing content for the web. Web content spec will be to content, what RSS is to web content distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Brightness Lock in Ubuntu 13.04</title>
      <link>http://sathishmanohar.com/brightness-lock-in-ubuntu-13-04/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://sathishmanohar.com/brightness-lock-in-ubuntu-13-04</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever Since I Upgraded to Ubuntu 13.04, the Brightness lock doesn’t work, After every few seconds it keeps reverting back to highest brightness level. While, I haven’t figured out the perfect solution, I relatively less painful temporary fix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only when I use the Fn + brightness keys in the keyboard, the brightness keeps reverting back to highest brightness. However, When I open the “Brightness &amp;amp; Lock” and drag the brightness slider, it seems to maintain the brightness setting until shutdown. Unfortunately after booting up I have to do this again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the setting I use in 13.04&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;full zoomable&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ubuntu-brightness-lock.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope it helps!&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>play snakes while your youtube video is loading</title>
      <link>http://sathishmanohar.com/play-snake-game-while-your-youtube-video-is-loading/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://sathishmanohar.com/play-snake-game-while-your-youtube-video-is-loading</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I was browsing through youtube today, suddenly my connection got cut off. I was starring at the loading animation. and naively pressed up arrow in the keyboard (click on the player, before pressing up arrow). I’m not bored anymore. Do it for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;full zoomable&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/youtube-snake-game.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Return 503 Service Unavailable or other specific HTTP Status Code</title>
      <link>http://sathishmanohar.com/how-to-return-503-service-unavailable-or-other-specific-http-status-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://sathishmanohar.com/how-to-return-503-service-unavailable-or-other-specific-http-status-code</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Recently major websites like reddit and wikipedia, decided to go black in protest of SOPA. This is when a Googler joined the conversation and instructed sites to go black the right way. In short &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/115984868678744352358/posts/Gas8vjZ5fmB&quot;&gt;Pierre Far&lt;/a&gt; instructed sites to return “503 Service Unavailable” Status code, to show bots, that the website in question was taken down, intentionally and temporarily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, Here are the various ways to return 503 status code. You can always customize these, to any other HTTP status, as you see fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;php&quot;&gt;PHP&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can set custom headers with PHP. Just include() this piece of code in the top of the pages, you want to blackout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-php&quot; data-lang=&quot;php&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;?php
header(&amp;quot;HTTP/1.0 503 Service Unavailable&amp;quot;);
?&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;plan-html-websites&quot;&gt;Plan HTML Websites&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To return specific HTTP Status codes in a Plain HTML Site, You can edit web server config. Include the Following snippet in .htaccess file in apache to achieve the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-apacheconf&quot; data-lang=&quot;apacheconf&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;pre class=&amp;quot;wp-code-highlight prettyprint&amp;quot;&amp;gt;# Don&amp;#39;t forget to turn on the rewrite engine
RewriteEngine on

# Maintenance Redirection
# Replace 555\.555\.555\.555 with your own IP address
# Uncomment first conditional to turn off the redirection
# RewriteCond %{REQUEST_URI} ^$a
# RewriteCond %{REMOTE_ADDR} !^555\.555\.555\.555$
# RewriteCond %{REMOTE_ADDR} !^127\.0\.0\.1$

# Here strike.html is the custom page, thats displayed
RewriteCond %{REQUEST_URI} !strike.html
# strike_files/ directory contains supporting files for strike.html
RewriteCond %{REQUEST_URI} !^/strike_files/

# Uncomment the below line, if you want to serve styles/ images/
# RewriteCond %{REQUEST_FILENAME} !(styles|images).+$

RewriteRule (.*) /strike.html [R=503,L]
ErrorDocument 503 /strike.html
&amp;lt;/pre&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For More Explanation about the code, visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://css-tricks.com/snippets/htaccess/temporary-maintenance-using-mod_rewrite/&quot;&gt;css-tricks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ruby-on-rails&quot;&gt;Ruby On Rails&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are Running a Ruby on Rails, Application. You can use the following snippets to set return specific HTML status codes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the entire application:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;# ApplicationController
before_filter :return_unavailable_status

private
def return_unavailable_status
render :nothing =&amp;gt; true, :status =&amp;gt; :service_unavailable
end&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you wanted a custom error page, you could do:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;render &amp;#39;custom_unavailable_page&amp;#39;, :status =&amp;gt; :service_unavailable&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t want it for specific controllers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;# SomeController, where you don&amp;#39;t want to display
# custom unavailable page
skip_before_filter :return_unavailable_status&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope this Helps! &lt;img src=&quot;http://sathishmanohar.com/wp-includes/images/smilies/icon_smile.gif&quot; alt=&quot;:)&quot; class=&quot;wp-smiley&quot; /&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for Stack Overflow user, &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/users/308315/iwasrobbed&quot;&gt;iWasRobbed&lt;/a&gt; For providing snippets for Rails Version.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>SOPA Hack</title>
      <link>http://sathishmanohar.com/sopa-hack/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://sathishmanohar.com/sopa-hack</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been reading about SOPA, Its very sad, Entertainment industry has taken the litigation route.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Brighter Side, SOPA has made protesting against it, easier than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple, Sing your favorite song and upload it to youtube. If you are not feeling adventurous, make it anonymous, by uploading it under a new account created with new email. Technically, Its still not bullet proof, but the more people do this, the more harder it is to crack down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Show a Sign, or annotate the video with “Stop SOPA” Message&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you Go. Thank Entertainment Industry for making possible, the Easiest Revolution Ever.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Why 9 to 5?</title>
      <link>http://sathishmanohar.com/why-9-to-5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://sathishmanohar.com/why-9-to-5</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve been doing web design/development for past 2 years, Even though I have office space, 9 to 5 never worked for me. I end up checking twitter, facebook, reading hacker news, techmeme, watching diggnation or Steve Jobs. I thought, this is a problem of mine. I was wrong. It is the problem of the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;factory&quot;&gt;Factory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It all starts with the “Factory”. Factories were places, where people got mass employment. Factories were run 9 to 5. But, Factories had very good reason to do that. It costs an awful lot to operate a factory. Nobody can run a factory between 4pm – 9pm, in favor of say, 40% of enthusiastic and efficient workers. Workers can’t get a shift between 6am – 10am, take a break, then come to work at 3pm – 7pm. It was just not possible, the system demanded that you’d be there, and punished for not being punctual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;knowledge-work&quot;&gt;Knowledge Work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, came the knowledge work. Knowledge work solely depends on creativity of the workers. But, still some how, knowledge work-places got modeled around factories. Employees had to work 9-5, be creative between 9-5, and go home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a problem, We cannot schedule brain to be creative at any given time. Sure, after sleep we are fresh, but fresh brain is not always, a creative brain. Modern day factories and tools are, a computer and/or a smartphone, which can work at the time of the user. But, still for some reason, knowledge workers are forced to work in rigid office hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-freedom&quot;&gt;Time Freedom&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m noting a new trend. I get more meaningful work done, early in the morning (sometimes before brushing) than I do in the office for half a day. Sometimes I get work done after 11pm, Sometimes I feel productive in a midnight moving train, and get few things done. The more I force myself to do something at certain time, the more I dislike the work, and end up coming up with duct-tape solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is not to procrastinate and postpone all the work to tomorrow, But, acknowledge that there are stuff to be done, and work on them, when you really want to work on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;synchronous-vs-asynchronous&quot;&gt;Synchronous vs Asynchronous&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While, this approach may work for per-determined, asynchronous work. i.e. you can choose which task to work on, at your time, when there is no other human involved with the actual work. Synchronous work still needs to be done at certain time. eg. appointments. Have good separation between synchronous and asynchronous tasks, work on asynchronous task at the time, you feel like working the task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach to work, has had a great positive effect on how I work. I hope it has the same effect on you.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I haven&#8217;t applied for YC</title>
      <link>http://sathishmanohar.com/why-i-havent-applied-for-yc/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author></author>
      <guid>http://sathishmanohar.com/why-i-havent-applied-for-yc</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It all started some time after &lt;a href=&quot;http://techcrunch.com/2011/01/28/yuri-milner-sv-angel-offer-every-new-y-combinator-startup-150k/&quot;&gt;jan 28 2011&lt;/a&gt;, I was following techcrunch on twitter then. After seeing a tweet about svangel and yuri milner’s investment in ycombinator companies, I thought ycombinator was some startup working on some hot trendy technology. But, the title doesn’t make a lot of sense, so I read the article and looked at ycombinator website. It was an aha moment. It was not a startup (in some way it is), but a hub for startups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It changed lot of my misconceptions. I knew about the valley and its the heart of technology. But, I thought its hard for foreign nationals to start companies in the valley. I was proven wrong in ycombinator FAQ. So, I decided to apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;excitement&quot;&gt;Excitement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I came to know about ycombinator by end of January 2011, application deadline was so close, and YC clearly states, early applications has significant advantage. So, I had to choose between one of my plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose the biggest (most toughest to execute), because, YC encouraged to act on bigger plans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Just as what we look for in founders is not the type of achievement but the magnitude, what we look for in ideas is not the type of idea but the level of insight you have about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I applied, then I started worrying about other things, like visa, what if I get accepted? will I get visa? What visa should I apply for? I knew nobody near valley at that time. I was freaking out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tweet_about_visa.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rejection&quot;&gt;Rejection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then the day came, I was rejected. Since, It all happened so fast, I got some time to think, after rejection. I’ll list what I did, what I have done wrong, and how am I correcting myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;full&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tweet_about_rejection.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;product-problem&quot;&gt;Product Problem&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was my plan? An Operating system based on Ubuntu, kinda Hybrid between Mobile, Tablets and PC. Why did I choose such a gynormous plan? Because, investors like to be part of bigger disruptive products. Since, big plans may attract funding, I thought I’d be okey. It was a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not that the idea was stupid. In fact, I want that product everyday. If I have enough money to start, I’ll make it happen. But, it was a mistake from another perspective. I had very little to contribute to building it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t done anything useful with compiled languages or hardware. So, I would have relied on others to build what I want, not so great for a startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;choose-right&quot;&gt;Choose Right&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I came up with three filters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What products I can build myself&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What products I will work on, regardless of funding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What I want the most&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was magic, when I applied these filters to all my ideas. It narrowed literally tens of ideas to two, I &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=2933420&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;decided to work on both.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;unknown&quot;&gt;Unknown&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since, I came to know about hacker news just before a month of application, I really didn’t interacted much with the community. I literally had 1 point in hacker news. Even though, points didn’t matter. My interactions, comments, submitted links were close to zero. I had a twitter account, that was all, it was the only public face I had. I realized that was a problem, So, I gradually started speaking up in Hacker News and started using Ask HN feature in Hacker News. It was awesome. People at HN are very helpful, wanting to hear from you, give valuable advice. I think it is great way to, get to know people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;real-product&quot;&gt;Real Product&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I applied Last time, I had an idea, only the idea. While ideas change the world. I realized everybody has ideas. So, I decided not pitch ideas anymore. I’ve built simple prototypes and gathered feedback. So, far everything looks good. I will build a minimum viable product, attract users, market the product, before seeking for funding or applying for accelerator programs. I think, I’ve done the right thing, Judging from recent &lt;em&gt;1 application per minute&lt;/em&gt; application submission rate for YC. Having MVP will clearly be an advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;will-apply&quot;&gt;Will Apply&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, This is my reason for not applying for current batch of YC. Now, I have a friend, who is working with me as well. We’ll apply once we have the product ready. The best thing that came out this decision, is that we are committed to a deadline now. So, Even if YC rejects our application next batch, We’ll have two promising products at our hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think of this decision? Is it good? or is it a mistake? I’ll be glad to hear from you all.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    

  </channel> 
</rss>
